Curriculum Vitae

Julien COLOMB, PhD in Biology Schillerpromenade 4 12049 Berlin julien.colomb@fu-berlin.de 030 46721825

https://github.com/jcolomb

http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520

Birth: 9 April 1979 in Sion (CH) Married, two children Swiss



Summary

After 12 years spent on fundamental research (neuro-genetics) in which I gathered skills in experimental design, team leading and student teaching, I got most interested in open science and research reproducibility as well as the digital tools helping scientists to achieve it. I would like to apply these novel knowledge to bring open science principles forward.

Research service activities

 $2018-current \quad Postdoctoral \ fellow, \ Friedrich-Schiller-University \ Jena \ (\textbf{Jena}, \ Germany), \ Information \ Postdoctoral \ fellow, \ Friedrich-Schiller-University \ Jena \ (\textbf{Jena}, \ Germany), \ Information \ Postdoctoral \ fellow, \ Friedrich-Schiller-University \ Jena \ (\textbf{Jena}, \ Germany), \ Information \ Postdoctoral \ fellow, \ Postdoctoral \ fellow,$

matic institute

Promoting data management with videos, an open source project.

Research activities

2014 - 2018 Postdoctoral fellow, HU and Charité (**Berlin**, Germany), by Prof. Y. Winter

9 month: R Shiny applications to analyse and archive behaviour sequence data.

7 month: Animal core facility director and project manager.

7 months: working on Phenobase.

2009 -2013 Postdoctoral fellow, FU (Berlin, Germany), by Prof. B. Brembs

working on "the what and where of operant learning in *Drosophila*".

2007-2008 Postdoctoral fellow, ESPCI (Paris, France), by Dr. T. Preat

working on "appetitive learning in *Drosophila*".

Commercial activities

2016-present Freelance scientist and open science trainer,

Project management, data analysis in R, literature curation, training workshop

organisation.

2012-present Founder and CEO of Drososhare GmbH (Berlin, Germany), facilitating fruit fly

transactions between scientists

Education

2016 FELASA B (working with rodents). HU Berlin

2013	Moderation & management (Continuing Education in team work and meeting
	organisation), FU Berlin/Artop.
2006	PhD in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg , Switzerland).
	PhD dissertation: "The chemosensory system of Drosophila larvae: neu-
	roanatomy and behaviour" Thesis director: Prof. R.F Stocker
2002	Diploma in Biology, University of Fribourg (Fribourg, Switzerland)
1998	"Maturité fédérale type C" (scientific subsection), in the "Collège de la royale
	Abbaye de St. Maurice"

Languages

French (mother tongue), English (fluent), German (fluent), Spanish (basics).

Computer skills

 $\label{eq:publishing: Publishing: Publis$

Organisation: Outlook, Access, labfolder; Image processing: Photoshop, Illustrator, Image J; Programming and data analysis: R, Rmarkdown, shiny, Git, Labview;

Research output

- 11 Research Papers (7 first author, 1 last author), 4 Reviews, 1 Scienceopen Collection
- 4 Open Source Software (3 main author),
- 3 Approved Grants
- > 25 Meeting Presentations

see https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3127-5520, https://github.com/jcolomb:

Supervision of students

2010-2014	Co-supervisor of the PhD student Christine Damrau (with Dr. B.Brembs) on
2008	the role of octopamine in reward, motivation and motor control in <i>Drosophila</i> . Co-supervisor of the PhD student Séverine Trannoy (with Dr. G. Isabel and Dr. N. Gervasi) on the role of dopamine in appetitive learning consolidation in
2005	Drosophila. Co-supervisor of the diploma work of Claire Huguenin (with Dr. A. Ramaekers) on the role of NO in olfactory discrimination in Drosophila larvae.

Teaching experience

2016	Animal models of neuropathy, (master student, 2x2h lecture, organisation)
2012	Genetik (bachelor, 2 x 3 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2012	Neurogenetik. (master, 2 x 2 h. lecture, 2x 1h. seminar)
2011	Practical course neurobiology. (7 x 4 h., Practical course supervision)
2011	Entwicklung der Insekten [Insect development] (2 h. lecture)
2006	Fluorescence and Confocal Microscopy (master, 3h. lecture)
2003-2006	Studying behavior. (master, 2 h. lecture)
2003-2005	Developmental- and Neurogenetics (master, 2 h. lecture).

Other tasks

Volunteer for FORCE11 communication, initiator of reagents.io open source project, Organisation of the Berlin Open Science meetup, Part of the march for science Berlin Orga team 2017 Creation of the T. Preat's and R.F. Stocker's lab website, Co-director in the theater group "les apostrophes" in 2006



Q.F.F.Q.S. SUMMIS AUSPICIIS SENATUS POPULIQUE FRIBURGENSIS

RECTORE MAGNIFICO
URSO ALTERMATT
HISTORIAE NOSTRORUM TEMPORUM PROFESSORE ORDINARIO

ORNATISSIMUS

JULIEN COLOMB

NATUS DIE IX MENSIS APRILIS A. D. MCMLXXIX

AD SUMMOS IN REBUS NATURALIBUS HONORES CONTENDENS DISSERTATIONEM SCRIPSIT CUI TITULUS

THE CHEMOSENSORY SYSTEM OF DROSOPHILA LARVAE: NEUROANATOMY AND BEHAVIOUR

QUAM ORDO MATHEMATICORUM ET PHYSICORUM DIE XXIV MENSIS NOVEMBRIS A.D. MMVI POST COLLOQUIUM RITE CUM EO PERACTUM COMPROBAVIT

ITAQUE CETERIS CONDICIONIBUS IMPLETIS

RERUM NATURALIUM DOCTOREM

EUM CREAVIT ET RENUNTIAVIT
TITUS JENNY
ORGANICAE ET ANALYTICAE CHEMIAE PROFESSOR
ORDINIS MATHEMATICORUM ET PHYSICORUM DECANUS

IN CUIUS REI FIDEM HOC PUBLICUM TESTIMONIUM UNIVERSITATIS SIGILLO SANCITUM EI TRADENDUM CURAVIMUS

FRIBURGI HELVETIORUM DIE XVIII MENSIS DECEMBRIS A.D.MMVI

H.T. RECTOR MAGNIFICUS

H.T. DECANUS